11. Appointment

Emily Stone sat in a small Italian cafe near Boston’s Battery Wharf, waiting for Joe Hartman. The cafe had an industrial chic aesthetic, with white ductwork on the ceiling, warm track lighting, and dark hardwood floors. Black shelves adorned the white walls, displaying random colorful objects, including a sailing boat model and bright artwork. The mixture of modern and rustic elements seemed symbolic of Joe’s and Emily’s different personalities.

Over the last twenty minutes, she had sent Joe two messages, asking if something had come up, but received no reply. His status was offline so that she couldn't call him. Annoyed and sure that Joe had been distracted by a computational problem or a pretty student, Emily decided to leave. It was like a flashback to the final days of their relationship. She grabbed her notebook and bag, frustrated with herself for agreeing to meet him. The crowded bus trip from Washington through New York to Boston had been such a hassle, and it ended up being totally pointless.

Joe had come to terms with the fact that the last few minutes were not a nightmare but a very real problem. Three kidnappers had assaulted him, the FBI had tried to arrest him for murder, and chaos ensued. One of Joe’s skills, developed after losing his parents, was the ability to compartmentalize—a trait well-meaning acquaintances described as ‘mastering the art of not giving a fuck.’

When the FBI agents and his assailants started to fight, Joe saw an opportunity. Instead of panicking, he methodically focused on his next steps. He needed time and a place to understand what was happening.

“Who were the kidnappers? What was wrong with the FBI? What had he gotten himself into?” Asking these questions made his head spin, so he shelved them for the moment. First things first.

The smoke and turmoil allowed him to scramble away unnoticed. But he knew the FBI could quickly track him using the city’s camera network, so he took steps to avoid being seen by any cameras. Where he can’t avoid them, he had to fool the face recognition algorithms, a topic he covered in one of his courses.

So Joe pulled a Patriots ball cap he had taken from a confused bystander low over his face, bought a pair of broad-bridged sunglasses and a gaudy scarf from a street vendor, and altered his gait by removing the insole of his left sneaker. Finally, he stuffed his black jacket into his backpack and shifted it to his front, changing his silhouette. Without a phone or smart glasses, he couldn't be tracked through mobile networks, which also meant he couldn’t reach out for help.

With a plan forming in his mind, he walked away slowly and purposefully.

After leaving the cafe, Emily went to the waterfront to clear her head. She was disappointed but not surprised by Joe. He was intelligent, charming, and successful but also unreliable and selfish. “That flaky jerk,” she thought to herself.

Looking out over the water, she watched a ferry cut through Boston Harbor, leaving a foamy wake. The city skyline and the bridges spanning the Charles River added to the picturesque view. The gentle lapping of waves momentarily distracted her from her thoughts.

Suddenly, she felt like she was being watched. Turning around, she saw people walking and talking on their smart glasses or earbuds—nothing out of the ordinary. Still, she couldn't shake the feeling.

Her phone buzzed in her pocket. It was probably Joe with an excuse she didn’t want to hear, so she ignored it. Regardless of what her editor thought, she would be writing a hell of a story about the car incident without Hartman. Lost in her thoughts, she was startled when a man appeared beside her.

“Hi, Emily,” he said softly.

23. Watchers

“It’s pretty clever to meet at the airport, One,” Hanson said softly into his microphone as he watched Emily Stone walk to the curb of Terminal B.

“Why is that so, Five?” Luke Brennan asked back, sitting in a black SUV parked 100 yards away, looking through the optics of his binoculars. After it became clear that Mercer was on the FBI team, he decided to stay in the background and provide overwatch. It was a given that Mercer had also realized who he had fought with in the morning when Joe Hartman’s apprehension went sideways.

“A public space with enough uniforms around but also not so crowded that you can’t see who’s around. But, here it comes,” Hanson said, obviously enjoying himself, “in the middle of a no-drone zone.”

“You’re bright kid, five, I have to give you that. But tell me, did that look like a planned meeting?” Brennan answered while rolling his eyes. His team had tailed the FBI agents from the Boston field office, hoping to gather intel on Hartman’s whereabouts or at least stay close when the FBI made its move.

Enrique Medenz, sitting next to Brennan with a rugged tablet in his hands, turned to him. “We’ve got an ID on the female, boss. Emily Stone is a journalist for the Washington Post. Seems like she knows our target pretty well. Check this out,” showing Brennan the image search result: a photo of Joe and Emily at a summer party, smiling and close.

“One, the lady is hailing a cab,“ he heard Hanson’s voice in his earpiece. “Do we follow her or stick with the FBI guys?”

Brennan made a quick decision, his gaze lingering on the image. “We stick with the lady. Move out.”

“So, what do we have? First, Mercer visited Bolt Industries, but we don’t know who they had been talking to,” Brennan started to recap the last hours.

“But we were able to stick the trackers to their ride,” Mendez nodded while driving behind the cab with a few cars between them.

“Yeah, that’s a plus. Then they went to Somerville and talked up David Donnelly, who obviously is also a buddy of our man Hartman. Then they legged it to Logan and caught Stone while she was about to leave.”

Brennan scratched his beard. “It looks like they are kicking some of Hartman’s friends and watching if they make a move. This tells me they have no idea where he is and hope that one of them is an associate of Hartman that leads them to him.”

“She’s getting off the cab, One,” he heard Mendez saying.

“That was just a short drive. Let’s see. Looks like she’s heading for the building with the dome structure. Three, you have eyes on her?”

“Roger, One. Following her,” Marty Decker, Spartan Three, replied.

“Four, deploy your toy,” Brennan said, hearing his Marines snickering to the tactical net.

“The drone, for Christ’s sake” Brennan clarified.

“Up in the air, One,” said Hanson, trying to keep his voice calm and just barely failing.

“Working just once with professionals,” Brennan mumbled as he got out of the car.

While following Emily Stone, Mendez updated Brennan with the information he read on his smart glasses: “This is the aptly named ‘Great Dome’, belonging to MIT.”

“Well, that’s the university where Hartman and Donnelly work. Maybe we get lucky,” Brennan answered while navigating the students and tourists roaming Killian Court.

“All callsigns, Spartan One. Move with caution. We don’t want to startle Stone.” Luke Brennan was acutely aware that he and his operatives did not blend in too well into the scenery, but if Emily Stone was to meet with Hartman, they had to be near and act swiftly and decisively.

“Any signs of the FBI, Four?”

“Negative, One. But I see two campus police walking the beat 100 meters south of your position.”

“Roger that, Five.” Brennan looked around the neatly maintained lawns, filled with young people lounging and the occasional frisbee player. It was not the best place to capture somebody unnoticed, and the egress posed a problem. Apart from the campus cops, it was hard to tell if FBI agents were on surveillance or if spotters had been positioned near the canopy trees that lined the court.

“One, we have movement on Donnelly’s car tracker,” Mendez informed him, standing right behind him, “heading south from his home. ETA to our position ten mikes.”

“Looks like the party is about to start. Three, status?” Brennan asked over the tactical network.

“Stone is sitting on the steps of the Dome and checks her phone about every other minute,” Decker answered softly, pretending to consult his phone himself, standing a few meters to her left.

After ten minutes, the tracker stopped moving two blocks from the Great Dome. Brennan and his team scanned the surroundings for several minutes for signs of Donnelly or Hartman.

“I’ve got a positive face recognition for Donnelly. He’s moving around the court like he’s out for a walk, occasionally stopping and looking around,” Hanson announced over the network.

“I think he’s doing something like a counter-surveillance walk,” Brennan answered after watching Donnelly’s movements carefully. “Not a pro, but not bad either,” he decided.

Finally, David arrived at the Dome’s steps. He approached Emily, and they exchanged a few words.

“Did anybody get what they are talking about? Did you listen in, Three?” Brennan asked urgently.

“Negative, but they are now walking away together,” Decker replied.

“Let’s not lose them. Move, move, move!” Brennan ordered his team while he checked his concealed holster with a quick and well-practiced movement.

25. High Level

After the meeting concluded, President Robert Weston stood behind the polished conference table and looked intently at the man standing next to him in the otherwise empty room. The table was scattered with name tags alongside some half-empty water bottles, marking the presence of high-level participants who had spent the last couple of hours discussing the implications of the Georgetown attack. Among them were the Secretaries of Homeland Security, Defense, and Commerce, as well as the Directors of the FBI, CIA, and NSA, and the most prominent leaders of the AI industry in the U.S.

“Mr President, you must reconsider the autonomous drone program,” Jason Bolt urged Weston.

“And why is this the case, Jason? Please enlighten me.”

“Because stopping it would send a fatal signal to the American people and our enemies. It’s a statement of weakness.”

“It’s my job to decide what’s in the best interest of the American people, and I can tell you that the slightest possibility of our drones starting a killing spree in our cities sends chills down my spine.”

Jason was shaking his head. “The cars were just a glitch in the grander scheme. Things like this happen at the forefront of innovation.”

Weston was taking a step back. “What are you trying to tell me, Bolt? I thought we were talking about the attack of psychopathic and begrudged professor?”

Bolt hesitated, realizing his slip. “Yes, that’s what I was trying to say. Autonomous cars, drones, and AI are safe. This was the work of a deranged personality. We just need to make sure this doesn’t happen again, people messing with the systems.”

Weston looked out of the large window of the meeting room into the blue, peaceful-looking sky, slowly nodding.

“Speaking of which, I understand that the FBI is still trying to get hold of Hartman?”

Weston turned his head back at Bolt. “He seemed to have simply vanished, which I find most peculiar. With all our face recognition algorithms and investigative AIs we’re unable to get hold of a single guy, a professor of all things, mind you, not some special operator type. And the report of unknowns that interfered with his arrest. This reminds me of times when our agencies played their private little games,” the President said while his eyes wandered over the name tags of the directors of the agencies at the table.

“I really want to know how Hartman pulled that off. It’s hard to believe that he did that single-handedly. But then again, AI is a powerful force multiplier, isn’t it, Jason?” He stared into Bolt’s eyes, which remained unfazed.

“If you want my advice, I suggest you don’t allow Hartman to explain his actions publicly. This would only unsettle the nation further. Or worse, encourage copycat terrorists. Instead, you should make an example of him and show what happens to people who attack the lifeline of our society. He’s today’s Osama bin Laden. He should go down spectacularly in blazing fire when they find him,” Bolt said, his eyes gleaming.

Weston crossed his arms, narrowing his eyes. “That’s not how we do it under my command, Mr. Bolt. We need to find the truth. For that, we need Hartman.”

“We need a strong leader who supports innovators during challenging times to help keep America great.”

“I beg your pardon?” Weston asked incredulously.

Jason took his time and peeled the label off a water bottle he had grabbed from the table as he began to speak.

“You understand me well. You remember, social media makes or breaks presidents. You want me and my algorithms on your good side if you want a second term, Bob,” Jason said, smiling after he delivered his only thinly veiled threat.

“But anyways, there are men ready to do what it takes,” Jason shrugged and dropped the bottle back on the table, making the President flinch.

And with that, he turned around and strode out of the conference room, leaving behind a bewildered Robert Weston, whom many still believed to be the most powerful man in the world. Jason Bolt wasn’t among them.

27. Prepping

David Donnelly quickly scanned the area for any sign of the men who had been watching him and Emily in Killian Court before unlocking his truck. Convinced that no one was around, he climbed into the vehicle and started the engine.

Driving through the streets of Boston, he tried to better understand who they were. He was pretty sure those guys were not law enforcement; they appeared more action-oriented and comfortable with direct physical interaction than with surveillance in academic or urban settings. They were professional nonetheless, moving efficiently and well-trained. It stood to reason that those were the same men who had tried to kidnap Joe earlier today. His money was on military operatives.

He checked the mirror to see if he could spot a tail but saw nothing suspicious. In times of ubiquitous camera-based surveillance, it was unnecessary to physically follow a car through a town's streets. Autonomous cars and cars with onboard AIs connected to the networks could be even more easily tracked. Basically, you knew where they would arrive before they even started rolling. But not his vintage pickup. It was one of the reasons why David happily stuck with it despite the apparent lack of digital comfort. Not that he had something to hide—at least not until today. It was just another bit of freedom that the digital society took away for the lull of more leisure, efficiency, and safety.

Once he was on the smaller roads in the countryside, the cameras would no longer be a problem. He chuckled. His little Walden was exactly where you could vanish from the connected world.

“Where’s he heading, Mendez?” Luke Brennan asked, glancing at the rugged tablet his second-in-command was studying. His team’s black SUV was weaving through the afternoon traffic at a safe distance from Donnelly’s truck.

“Looks like he’s heading home, Cap.”

“We’ll hang around the neighborhood but keep out of sight. I don’t want him to see us lurking in the streets.”

David was going through the things they would need in the cabin for the next few days: food, fresh clothing, and a satellite phone for emergencies. While holding the phone in his hand, he wondered how his meeting with Emily had quickly attracted uninvited guests. He had assumed that Emily was being followed from the airport. The FBI had found her there, but he could have led the team to Killian Court. He had to consider all variables and options.

So he took out his phone and pondered the best way to prevent it from becoming a tracking device. Turning it off wouldn’t be enough, though. Even turned off, phones can occasionally connect to networks, making them trackable unless the battery is completely drained. Even with the battery removed, it would still happily broadcast its ID to government scanners using RFID technology.

He needed a miniature Faraday cage, which was nothing more than a metallic mesh blocking electromagnetic signals. David loved tinkering with hardware and had some in his garage.

As he entered the brightly lit room, smelling faintly of gasoline, his eyes rested on his truck. A thought occurred to him, and he slapped his forehead.

He went to the cabinet next to his workbench and looked around until he found what he had been searching for. A few years ago, he had created a simple device to find open WiFi networks for an engineering class. It consisted of a microcontroller, a software radio module, and an antenna. After a quick code update, it would also scan long-range transmission frequencies. He opened his laptop on the workbench and started typing. After rebooting the device a minute later, he was rewarded with two strong signals on the small display.

“Fuck my life,” David muttered as he crawled under his truck with a flashlight.

“One, there seems to be a problem with the gyroscope in the tracker,” Mendez alarmed Luke Brennan, sitting next to him with his eyes closed. Like every soldier, Brennan had mastered the art of sleeping wherever possible, even for just a few minutes.

But now he was wide awake. “What has happened? Have we lost the signal?”

“No, but it was a sudden, quick change in vertical position, see?” Mendez pointed to a chart on his tablet.

“Maybe it fell off because you know who didn’t affix it correctly,” Brennan said, turning to Hanson in the backseat.

“Or maybe he loaded something heavy into his truck bed?” Hanson offered and shrugged.

“Uh, it could be anything, Cap. But honestly, I don’t know. The signal might be disturbed by stuff in his garage,” Mendez scratched his head.

“Alright, we need eyes on the car. Decker, head to Donnelly’s place, find cover and keep watch. Double time!”

“Well, well, well, look what we’ve got.” David carefully placed the two magnetic trackers on the metal toolbox in his truck bed, exactly as he found them. He examined the sophisticated devices, pondering his next move. He wasn’t sure how accurately their position would be signaled, but he didn’t want to take any chances. The small trackers looked sophisticated enough to contain gyroscopes and accelerometers to help locate their position, even if GPS signals weren’t available or disturbed.

He would have probably overlooked the second device if he hadn’t detected two signals. He would run the scanner in the cabin again to avoid nasty surprises.

He looked at the trackers and stroked his beard, pondering his options. He could leave them here and try to sneak out or shield them like he did with his phone. The latter would give him away immediately; he was sure that if they stopped broadcasting, this would alarm his pursuers. Leaving them here only worked if nobody was watching his home.

Whoever had placed the trackers wanted to know where he was going without having him under constant surveillance, so this offered him a third option, which was worth a try. He looked forward to the little surprise.

David returned to the kitchen, took the prepared supplies, and whistled as he carried them to his truck. After everything was in place, he slowly rolled out of the garage onto the quiet street of his Somerville home, feeling a pang of excitement.

39. Loose Ends

Jack McBride glared at his tablet, the live video feeds from Maine only deepening his foul mood. He desperately needed a Scotch to take the edge off, but drinking in the office was never an option. He was a man of many vices, he had to admit to himself. But also very effective in hiding them. That’s what brought him here, to the desk of the Director of the FBI: always willing to do what has to be done.

The live video feeds on his tablet showed different views of the site in Maine where FBI agents and the Beavercreek PD were combing through the charred remains of a cabin in the woods. The forensic teams still had to find any evidence that Joe Hartman had been there when it blew up. This didn’t stop the SENTINEL widget on his screen from showing high confidence that the threat was neutralized. The investigative AI still was a black box to him, and McBride’s career wasn’t exactly rooted in law enforcement but rather in knowing the right things about the right people. But even for him, it was hard to believe that public enemy number one, Professor Joseph Hartman, accidentally killed himself with a few kilograms of C4 while tinkering with some IED, a homemade bomb.

It didn’t improve his disposition that a notification of an encrypted call popped up on his not-so-official phone, announcing Jason Bolt.

“I’m in the office,” he answered instead of a greeting when he accepted the call.

“And I thought you were already celebrating with some pretty girls covered in fairy dust. That would have explained why you forgot to thank me.”

McBride winced at the mention of ‘fairy dust,’ an exclusive designer drug that promised very vivid hallucinations without the hangover—fulfilling your fantasies without being addictive. He wasn’t sure about the latter, as he looked very much forward to his next trip.

“You mean the fuckup in Maine? Yeah, thanks a lot. I thought we agreed on you giving me the coordinates, and I’m taking care of the rest. There’s no trace of Hartman or his associates.”

“Well, I took the initiative. He went in and never came out again. That is good enough for me. Just leak the story on social media and keep an open eye. Either we’ve settled the matter, or we flush out Hartman. Every device we are on is listening and looking out for him, Donnelly, and Stone. And that’s a lot of devices. I mean, we were even on the memory pack he carried around. It took a bit until a drone picked up the signal, but I can live with that. Worst case, he’s a dead man walking, Jack.”

“I’m more concerned about the talking, not the walking, Jason. What if he or his journalist girlfriend starts spreading the news?”

“Ah, always the skeptic. We’re not amateurs like your NSA; I see and hear everything that floats through the networks. And I control most of them as well. Remember that, Jack.”

McBride flinched at the thinly veiled threat. “No need to remind me. I know what you’re capable of; believe me. Anything else?”

“Yep. That rogue agent Mercer of yours. He seems to be a bit tricky to contain. As far as I know, he hooked up with his old buddies, including that prick Clayton. May I suggest a course of action?”

“I would be delighted,” McBride replied, his voice dripping with sarcasm.

“He’s a bit bromantic, so he will contact his partner and speak his mind sooner than later. We need to know what he’s up to. Let Lin back into the game, but make sure we also have tabs on him.”

“Okay, we can do that.” The FBI’s director had to admit that Bolt had a point. Mercer was a loose cannonball and Lin might offer an angle on him.

“After the talking is done, you finish them off. It’s time to tie up loose ends. Understood? And then relax, Jack. By the way, did you know that fairy dust was discovered by one of our AI projects? See, I do make the world a better place,” Bolt grinned.

“Ah, fuck off, Jason.” McBride closed the connection with an angry tap on the screen. If the devil ever walked amongst us, Jason Bolt was a strong contender, he thought. And he had sold his soul a long time ago in exchange for secrets being kept and favors being done.

When Jake Lin left the office of Deputy Director Helen Koop, he was carrying his badge and his Glock again. After a sleepless night with quite some discussions at home, he was ordered to see Koop in the early morning and expected the worst. But it went rather smoothly instead, at least at the surface.

He pondered the implications of being reinstated so quickly, realizing it was less about trust but necessity. The bureau obviously needed him, but he felt like a pawn moved around in a convoluted chess game when he thought about it.

Much of the conversation was centered around his partner, Alex Mercer, and speculation about why he had gone rogue. Jake had to admit that he wasn’t entirely sure what had driven Mercer in the last 24 hours but kept it to himself. Whatever it was, he trusted Alex had good reasons. Koop had talked about loyalty, and Jake was more sure than ever that he knew where he was standing.

When he left the FBI Field Office in Washington, the morning sun shone in a blue sky, and birds sang. It felt like they were mocking him.

45. Change of Plans

General Richard Clayton, his index finger tapping impatiently on the desk, looked sternly at his aide. “So, you aborted the mission to neutralize Bolt. Why? What did you find?”

“Sir, Doctor Hartman was able to access the information Herzog carried with him to our meeting,” Captain Steven Monroe answered and looked over to Joe. “Maybe it’s best if he explains what he found.”

Joe inhaled sharply. “The short version is a dead man’s switch. The long version is that we have reason to believe Bolt is the only one able to access the backdoor.”

“Which sounds like a good thing, Doctor. Get Bolt and close the backdoor, right? Can’t we incapacitate him and short-wire the goddam switch?” Clayton interrupted him.

“The problem is, we are talking about a neural implant, General. Just a thought might be enough to activate whatever Bolt has planned. And if we understand it correctly, if the implant registers any change in his physiological state, it may also activate any preprogrammed contingencies.”

“Being dead counting as such a state change,” Monroe added helpfully.

“It might be possible to disconnect Bolt from the network, but honestly, I expect this would also trigger a reaction,” David said.

Clayton buried his face in his hands and groaned. “Let me get this right,” he said when he looked up again, “if the bastard slipped and broke his neck, the world as we know it could end?”

“That sums it up—the ultimate narcissistic middle finger,” Joe said. I’m not a specialist in neuroimplants, but they usually work both ways. They let the blind see and the deaf hear again. So he’s sending commands and getting input from the implant, making it even harder to get to him.”

“This is just fucking awesome,” Alex Mercer, who had been silent until now, swore.

“Alright, folks. The situation is messed up, so let’s see if we can fix it,” Joe said. “Every system has its flaws.”

Emily and David turned to Joe as one and looked surprised. “That’s pretty insightful for someone like you, Mr. AI-is-perfect,” Emily said, smiling.

“If there’s something I learned the hard way in the last twenty-four hours, it’s this: humans make technology, and so it’s as flawed as its creators,” Joe answered with a shrug.

“Have you considered the technology itself a problem, Hartman?” Clayton asked him with a hint of menace. “Artificial intelligence, where even its creators don’t know how it really works inside the box, autonomous drones, autonomous cars, brain implants, social media. They unravel the social fabric and transform people into mindless drones without guilt or conscience. Your technology is outright destructive.”

Joe pointed his finger at Clayton. “Is the rifle the problem or the man pulling its trigger? I’ll tell you what, you just can’t trust people. Digital technology is no more or less than a force multiplier for human decisions.”

“There are people you can trust, Joe,” Emily said, laying her hand on his arm.

“Maybe we can go back to the point where we were talking about unfucking the situation,” David said, stepping forward. “I think you’re both correct. There’s a flaw in the system—and technology, if you will—and it’s likely the human part. So, there needs to be some control in place. Let’s make the abstract tangible: How do we control the backdoor and lockout Bolt before we reach the point of no return?”

Alex Mercer rubbed his eyes. “Can we do the same thing as with the evidence bags? Trick the system into believing Bolt’s implant is a happy camper, faking its signal?”

“Good thinking, Alex. But for that to work, we must understand what the implant is transmitting. So, we must approach Bolt closely to gather sufficient data for building a model. If, and that’s a big if, the transmitter we have from Herzog can listen in on the conversation,” David said, slowly shaking his head. “It’s not like sniffing data packets in an unsecured WiFi network.”

“And if we do it the other way around?” Steven Monroe joined in. “Make Bolt’s brain or the implant believe everything is okay?”

“Sounds a bit like The Matrix,” Emily said thoughtfully.

“Come again?” Mercer asked, clearly not getting the reference.

“It’s a classic movie. The machines put people into pods to harvest their energy and let the humans think they are living their everyday lives to keep them happy. A big simulation. That’s The Matrix,” David explained.

“Didn’t Bolt believe we all live in a simulation?” Monroe asked.

“No, that was another one,” Joe said absentmindedly.

“But it could work, theoretically. Feeding his visual and auditory cortex with generated content, like a virtual reality game,” David concluded.

“Don’t forget the sensory inputs, like touch, temperature, muscle tension,” Joe added.

“Total Immersion,” Emily said, snapping her fingers. That’s a super-hyped startup building hyper-reality games. It puts people into a sensory deprivation tank, floating in darkness, and gets all those inputs fed directly into the brain. They do this with biodegradable nanoparticles that you must inhale through the nose, which travel the nerve pathways directly to the brain. They act as transmitters for the simulation.”

“Creepy,” Mercer shuddered.

“Sounds great, but how do we get Bolt into one of those tanks without triggering his implant’s failsafe?” Captain Monroe asked.

“Times were considerably easier when you just put a bullet in the bad guy’s brain and were done with it,” Clayton remarked after listening silently for the last few minutes. “But adapt and overcome. So we need to commandeer one of those tanks, the magic nasal spray, and a … game?”

“The SEALs have such tanks in their ‘Mind Gym,’ sir. If I recall correctly, SEAL Team Six uses them at the Naval Amphibious Base Coronado,” Monroe said. “And they use nanoparticles for enhanced learning and simulations.”

“Unfortunately, California is not exactly around the corner, Captain,” Clayton remarked.

David added, “But the University of Texas works closely with the DoD, right? They may have one or two in Austin; isn’t that where Bolt was going tonight?”

“Seems like our best shot. Monroe, check with the university and make sure we have a Globemaster on standby at Andrews. Get the team ready to deploy to Austin. And you four as well,” Clayton gestured firmly towards Mercer, Joe, David, and Emily as he spoke.

“Yeah, but what do we do once we have Bolt in the tank?” Joe asked Clayton, who was already on the move.

After a quick calculation in his mind, he smirked. “You’ll have two and a half hours in the air to figure it out, professor.”

Rebecca Hayes paced her office, shaking her head in disbelief. The call with the polite but adamant Marine captain had just derailed her plans.

She should have been packing for her trip to Washington now, but this guy, Monroe, had just requisitioned her laboratory and her with it.

“It would be very unfortunate indeed if the General had to advise the Department of Defense not to renew your university’s contract,” he had said without leaving a doubt about his intentions.

Tears welled up in her face, more out of frustration than anything else. She had pleaded with him, telling him about Maria’s trauma and why she needed to be on this flight to Washington. Finally, he had conceded to promising her a ride on an Air Force plane later tonight. She wasn’t sure if she could trust the offer, but there weren’t many choices. If she lost her position at the university, she couldn’t help Maria anyway, as the young Marine had pointed out.

“That sun of a bitch just blackmailed me,” she swore to herself.

With a heavy sigh, she dropped into her chair behind her desk. She stared at the wall for a moment, gathering her thoughts. “Vesta, clear the pods’ schedule after six p.m. tonight and tell everybody the lab’s off-limits for a classified military experiment.”

46. In the Air

Jason Bolt strode leisurely over the tarmac at Boston Logan International Airport to board the Boom Sonata hypersonic business jet, branded with the Bolt Industries logo. A flight attendant in a form-fitting uniform smiled brightly at him at the gangway.

“Welcome aboard, Jason,” greeted a young woman with a blonde pixie cut.

“Thanks, Carol. How’s the yoga certification coming along?”

She beamed. “Super happy with the course, thank you!”

As he stepped into the cabin, he had already forgotten her name and hobbies. The ephemeral information his implant provided wasn't worth memorizing. He had more important things on his mind.

The flight time was less than two hours at Mach 1.8. Enough time to review intel on Hartman and his crew and plan the next steps. Joe teaming up with the General was unlikely but not unpredicted. The probability they’d find information in Herzog’s stuff was low. It proved Gideon had been brilliant, albeit misguided. It’s a shame he had to shut him down. But no one is irreplaceable—except the exception that proves the rule. Bolt smiled.

He leaned back in the reclinable leather seat and selected a massage program, his insanely expensive German sneakers scattered on the plush floor. Austin was going to be fun, Bolt thought and closed his eyes.

Joe Hartman walked up the loading ramp of the C-17 Globemaster III at Joint Base Andrews, awe-struck by the vast, utilitarian space. The cargo bay was empty except for an ambulance in the center, painted white with green and yellow chevron striping and labeled “United States Army Ambulance Service.” Joe wondered where Clayton had requisitioned the vehicle, assuming the General had called in several favors for the operation on such short notice. Fold-down seats lined the bare metal walls, occupied by a handful of men in civilian clothing, strapped in with rifles secured beside them.

The loadmaster directed him to his seat next to Emily, Mercer, and David, pointing to the noise-canceling headsets plugged into the intercom system. “You’ll need those, sir, to stay in the loop,” the sergeant explained and moved on.

Captain Monroe, seated on the opposite side of the cargo bay, gave him a thumbs up. Joe felt alone in the enormous military plane as he fastened his unusually tight seatbelt.

The large ramp started to move upwards, the servos whining. With every inch, less daylight remained until the ramp locked in place, closing the bay.

“Lima Three One Seven, ready for takeoff. Be advised thunderstorms are in the forecast, so we will have a rough ride. Stand by for departure,” the pilot’s voice came loud and clear over the headsets. The hum of the engines grew louder, vibrating through his seat as the aircraft started taxiing. Joe looked around for barf bags but found none. He closed his eyes, trying to calm the queasiness in his stomach.

Joe heard Alex Mercer’s voice over the intercom a few minutes after takeoff. The plane’s steep curve didn't sit well with his stomach.

“Alright, guys, this is our channel. We’ll hear the flight crew’s announcements; otherwise, it’s private. So, how are we going to play this?” Mercer gestured at the six men beside Captain Monroe. “We have a snatch team, a shooter, and a spotter. Scott will shoot Bolt with a tranquilizer dart. We must rush the prick to the next station because the implant might trigger the failsafe anytime.”

David nodded. “And we have the Immersive Learning Lab at UT Austin. Two float tanks with VR projectors. Enough nanoparticle spray to let Bolt dream for a week. His brain may fry before that, though. The recommended maximum usage is sixty minutes every forty-eight hours.”

“Bolt’s well-being is the least of my concerns,” Joe said. “But if something triggers the implant, we’re screwed.”

Monroe looked serious. “So, we have a time limit. Maybe two hours if we're lucky. We can't waste a second. Once he's in the simulation, what’s the plan?”

“Get him to tell us how to disable his implant or the backdoor,” David said. “Not likely, I know.”

Emily shook her head. “I don’t see how we can get a psychopath like Bolt to cooperate.”

Joe remembered his conversation with General Clayton. “Every system has a flaw,” he said more to himself than the others. “And Jason, being Jason, maybe he’s the one.”

Mercer spoke again. “Hartman, you’re the AI expert and know him best. You’re working on making the simulation realistic and trying to interface with his implant with David, okay? Emily, you’re the one with words and analysis. You should be scripting the scenario for Bolt. Monroe handles logistics and liaises with the university. No offense.”

Monroe nodded. “None taken. Making things happen is my job. What about you?”

“I’ll ensure nobody interferes while we snatch him and he's in the tank. Mendez and his boys know how to handle a rifle, but sometimes you have to point them in the right direction,” he said, looking at Sergeant Mendez, who winked in return.

Joe took a deep breath. This wasn’t a plan; it was a rough sketch. They had one shot, and failure wasn’t an option.

After playing with scenarios in his head, Jason Bolt made a decision that was not based on his implant's probabilities. The mental picture of a showdown in Austin, two gunslingers at noon, was much more exciting than playing it safe. Well, it wouldn’t be noon, and the Austin Convention Center wasn’t a place for tumbleweed, but having Hartman at gunpoint made up for this. And it was Texas, after all.

His intel was sketchy, as the U.S. military was tight-assed about using AI, thanks to old bastards like Clayton, but that was about to change. Circumstantial information like flight plans, passenger manifests, and Jake Lin’s surveillance indicated they were striking tonight. After Herzog’s device briefly connected with the network, he knew they probably accessed Gideon’s smuggled data.

He unlocked his tablet and tapped Jack McBride’s contact. A few moments later, the FBI Director appeared on the screen, looking worse than their last call.

“How are the preparations for Austin?” Bolt asked unceremoniously.

“The protection detail will meet you at the runway, Jason. The San Antonio Division is all over Austin. I still wonder if your own security wouldn’t be enough. This isn’t subtle.”

“Well, based on the taxes I paid last year, you’re all on my payroll anyway. And if it gets messy, you know, all this paperwork,” he rolled his eyes theatrically. “And if your guys finally take down Hartman, consider it a bonus. Eliminating public enemy number one should be worth it, right?”

“A public enemy of your own making.”

“That’s what I do, Jack. I create and destroy,” he said, tapping his right temple with his index finger. “All with the power of my mind. Almighty, if you will.”

The 5K video feed showed the glimmer in Jason’s eyes. Invisible to Joe, McBride’s hands started trembling under his desk as he realized Jason Bolt wasn’t joking.

Bolt closed the connection without goodbyes. He had another call to make for his next chess move.

He loved a good game but preferred tipping the odds in his favor.

47. Arrested

Joe gripped his armrests, counting each agonizing second until landing. He hated flying, and the turbulent approach to Austin was a nightmare. Across the cargo bay, Marine Captain Steven Monroe's tense movements caught his eye as he retrieved his phone. Joe's unease deepened. Something was definitely wrong.

“I owe you one, buddy,” General Richard Clayton said as he read the message on his private phone: “Cover Your Six.”

As midshipmen in Annapolis, this warning from his former roommate, Rear Admiral Leroy Harris, often meant trouble was on the horizon. Now, Harris’s position in the Department of Defence gave it a whole different quality. He hastily deleted the message and tapped out a warning to his aide. The moment he hit send, he could hear the commotion in the hallway. Clayton stood up and straightened his combat utility uniform, bracing for whatever was coming.

“Listen up,” Monroe’s voice came on the team’s channel over the plane’s intercom. “We don’t have much time.”

“Nothing new,” David grunted and leaned forward.

“I just got a warning from the General. We’re going to have company on the ground,” Monroe continued. “Hartman, Mercer, you’re our best bet stopping Bolt. Honestly, there’s no chance this works, but we will try it anyway. We need to get you out of here.”

As Joe followed Monroe’s eyes, he realized with horror that the captain was looking at the ambulance. Alex Mercer was already releasing his seatbelt and motioned for Joe to do the same. When Joe put away the headphones, he was washed over by the engines’ rumbling noise and the plane’s rattling. Just as he stood, the plane violently lurched as it hit turbulence. Joe nearly crashed on the floor as he tripped over his feet—but caught himself at the last moment. Mercer stood beside him and gave him a small nod, which Joe returned. Swerving through the cargo bay, they covered the few paces to the ambulance. Joe opened the backdoor and climbed in, followed by Mercer, who closed the door with a thud, leaving most of the noise outside.

The confined space of the ambulance offered only one seat for an attendant next to the gurney. Three large black pelican cases were fixed to the bench on the other side of the ambulance. As the plane tilted to the left, both men had to hold on to the gurney straps to right themselves.

“We need to get strapped in for landing,” Mercer said, pushing past a dumbfounded Joe. Once in the attendant’s seat, he gestured at the gurney. “Make yourself comfortable.”

“You must be kidding!” Joe shook his head just as the next turbulence hit the plane.

Mercer just shrugged as he adjusted the seatbelt.

Gloomily, Joe lowered himself onto the gurney and was nearly thrown off the stretcher by another violent move of the Globemaster. He fastened the straps as well as he could and cursed silently.

In the cargo bay, Steven Monroe switched the intercom channel to the team of operators next to him. “Marines, you haven’t seen this.”

Scott, the shooter, looked up from his tablet. “No idea what you’re talking about, Cap.” The other marines just nodded, and Mendez stifled a bored yawn.

Monroe took a deep breath, anticipating what would wait for them once they were on the ground again.

Clayton’s office door swung open with a firm push. Three armed military police entered the room, one of them a young lieutenant, followed by two agents in dark blue windbreakers with “FBI” stenciled in bold yellow letters. Finally, two plainclothes agents stepped in, wearing badges around their necks.

The older of the two suits approached the General and looked him sternly in the eyes.

"General Richard Clayton, Department of Defense Criminal Investigation Service. You are under arrest for charges including aiding and abetting, obstruction of justice, and conspiracy. Lieutenant, read the General his rights.”

While the Lieutenant was visibly taut as he held the small plastic card on which he read the Miranda rights, one of the enlisted MPs stepped forward with a pair of handcuffs.

The tension in the room was palpable as everybody watched the general being taken into custody.

Clayton curtly nodded at the lieutenant and said, “Those won’t be necessary.”

The lieutenant looked at the DoD agent, who was obviously in charge of the operation, with an unspoken question. He gave a barely perceptible nod, and the two armed MPs lined up to Clayton’s left and right before the group moved out of the office.

After the Globemaster had touched the ground, the pilot’s deep voice came over the intercom: “Heads up, we’re going to be boarded for inspection. Everybody remains seated. I repeat, everybody remains seated.”

Emily’s heart pounded in her ears, her anxiety building. David squeezed her hand and flashed an encouraging smile. She looked over to the Marines on the opposite side, who seemed pretty bored—except for Steven Monroe. The Captain was alert, his tension clearly visible.

When the plane stopped taxiing and the engines powered down, David lifted his headphones, and Emily followed his example. He leaned over to her. “Our best chance is to keep calm and look like we know what we’re doing. Feeling a bit wired up is okay, but don’t let them see your fear,” he said, winking at her.

The large ramp started to lower, rain patting heavily on the plane’s hull and the outside tarmac. Emily craned her neck to have a better look. She saw the soldiers surrounding the perimeter, wearing black tactical vests over their cammies with “Military Police” penciled in bold white letters on the front, their M4 carbines at the low ready. She felt like the time was slowing down, her trepidation rising with every breath. After everything she had been through over the last thirty-six hours, it looked like their escape would come to an end. She wondered how David could remain so calm in the presence of the soldiers outside.

Once the ramp stopped moving, a group of MPs started to march into the cargo bay, led by a master sergeant with a neatly trimmed brown mustache. Their heavy boots hitting the floor echoed through the confined space. They halted in front of Monroe. He rose slowly to signal he was posing no threat.

“Captain Monroe,” Master Sergeant Thomas Huffman saluted sharply.

“Master Sergeant,” Monroe returned the salute.

“Sir, I am here under direct orders of the Department of Defense Criminal Investigation Service. You are charged with aiding and abetting, obstruction of justice, and conspiracy. You are to be taken into custody effective immediately.”

The Master Sergeant gestured at the MPs who had followed him. “Secure the Captain’s service weapon and communications devices.”

After Monroe handed them over, the Master Sergeant continued to read him his rights. He then asked if he had fully understood.

“Affirmative,” Monroe answered without emotion in his voice.

Huffman addressed the other passengers. "The rest of you, listen up. I'm taking operational command here on the ground. Sergeant Mueller will escort you to the marked MP vehicles on the airfield. You will be transported to Camp Mabry, awaiting further instructions. Let's move out!”

David and Emily stayed in their seats as the others walked out of the ramp after confirming their orders. The master sergeant turned to them with a surprised look on their face.

“What about you two? Do you need an extra invitation?”

“With all due respect, Master Sergeant,” David said, “but I don’t think your orders apply to civilians.”

The Master Sergeant looked uneasy when he realized the others had already left the Cargomaster.

“Being on a military aircraft, nonetheless. What is your business here anyway?”

“I’m not allowed to disclose this to you, Master Sergeant. It’s definitely above your pay grade,” David replied.

Emily was aghast. What was going on here?

As a passionate poker player, David was not afraid to bluff but truly hoped this one wouldn’t be called. “Either you have something to charge us with, or…”

Master Sergeant Thomas Huffman was long enough in the military to know self-initiative is not always the best course of action. He took his tablet out of the cargo pocket of his pants and studied the file he had received half an hour ago. Unfortunately, his orders were a bit fuzzy, at least in the second part: arrest one Captain Monroe, establish command and control over the other personnel, and get them to Mabry. As he was thinking how that stubborn man in front of him might fit into this, with his unwavering air of authority that set off his instincts, he heard someone coming down the metal ladder from the flight deck.

“Hey, are you done here?” The voice of the buff Air Force major, whom Emily recognized from the intercom as the pilot, echoed through the hull.

“We have orders to refuel and return to Andrews in twenty, so make it snappy,” he continued as he approached the small group.

Huffman quickly considered his options. “Yes, Major, we’re done. I’ll leave you to attend to your freight.”

Before the baffled pilot could respond, the MP had turned around and made it down the ramp double time.

“If you and your crew could help us with the truck releases, we’ll be on our way in five minutes,” David said, gesturing at the ambulance, while Emily smiled warmly at the Air Force officer, still not believing what she had just witnessed.

“Did you understand any of this?” Joe Hartman asked Alex Mercer, sitting on the gurney. There had only been muffled voices, so Mercer shook his head.

Suddenly, the metallic clank of holds being released was clearly audible in the ambulance, and the front doors opened and closed.

A beep and a flashing light next to the headset fixed on the wall right to Mercer’s seat made both men look in its direction.

“Go,” Mercer answered the incoming call, and after listening a few seconds, he ended it with “Affirmative.”

He looked at the puzzled Joe and said with a smile: “You better strap in again, Hartman.”

“No fucking way, Mercer.”

49. In Position

“Isn’t that your partner, Mercer?” Emily asked, pointing at the screen showing Bolt’s parade through the Austin Convention Center. She had been scrutinizing the footage for the last few minutes.

Alex Mercer had just returned from reconning the center. “I don’t know why he’s with Bolt, but that’s Jake. And plenty of Feds. Bolt’s got close protection now.”

“And the place is packed with flying cameras,” Joe Hartman said. “That’s not helping, either.”

“I anticipated many cameras, but this leaves no blind spots. They will identify any of us in seconds if we waltz in there,” David Donnelly said, scratching his head. “No chance to bring a tranquilizer gun in unnoticed either.”

“Well, the drones could be not only the problem but also part of the solution here,” Joe said thoughtfully without taking his eye off the screen. “I guess we can sneak one or two of our own in there.”

“Where are you going, Joe?” David asked.

“We use Bolt’s playbook. What’s the payload of our drones?”

“They’re small surveillance drones; you could add a few grams but not enough to deliver explosives, as Bolt did. You’d need cargo drones for that.”

“Honestly, this ain’t good enough. Too many points of failure, and we literally have only one shot. And we’re running out of time,” Mercer said, pointing to the interactive floor plan that was opened on the other laptop. “We’ll have to do it old-fashioned. Bolt will be speaking in the Great Ballroom on the 4th floor. We go in with flashbangs. In the chaos, the close protection detail will try to bring their charge out of the building on the fastest route, the service elevator here, which goes straight to the loading area on the street level. They will be their most vulnerable when they get out of the elevator and try to get him into one of their cars. That’s where we will strike. We shoot Bolt with the tranquilizer gun and neutralize the agents.”

After a short pause, Mercer continued. “No lethal force. We incapacitate only. Understood?” He looked sternly at David, who raised his hands in a mock surrender.

"Straightforward. Let's do it,” David said.

“You know how to handle a rifle?”

David Donnelly nodded enthusiastically.

“Emily and I are going to take care of the security guards at the loading bay,” Mercer continued.

“How’s that? Why me?” Emily asked nervously.

“You’ll distract them before I take action. Then you’ll be our designated driver. Get the ambulance to the loading area. And floor it to the university’s lab once we have Bolt. Accustom yourself to the route; there will be no navigation on board, thanks to David.”

David shrugged with a smile.

Mercer turned to Joe. “You have any experience with close-quarters combat?”

Joe shook his head.

“You can open a can of Coke?”

Joe nodded, unsure where Mercer was going.

“A flashbang isn’t so much different. So this is settled. I’ll wait for Bolt’s security detail and ambush them when they exit the elevator. Once David has shot every dart we have, he’ll join me in the fight. To kick it off, go up and throw the grenades, then get the hell out of there and back down to help us,” he pointed at Hartman.

All eyes were on Joe, who swallowed heavily and nodded.

Mercer scrolled through the floor plan on the laptop.

“There’s a skywalk from the Hilton hotel to the fourth floor of the convention center, above East Fourth Street. This should get you pretty close to your strike point. There will be some security at the bridge, but definitely less than at the center’s official entrance. You’ll need to get creative.”

“A skywalk?!” Joe went pale. He had always suffered from vertigo, and his thoughts went back to that humiliating school trip. He shuddered.

“Everything okay?” Emily asked, placing her hand on his shoulder. Joe straightened a bit and nodded.

“How do I get past the security cameras in the hotel?” Joe asked.

“I have an idea, but it won’t be pleasant,” David said apologetically.

“Man, moving anything on my face damn hurts,” Joe said, who looked swollen and disfigured, after David had used saline injections to alter the proportions of his face.

"Focus, Hartman. Get moving and keep a low profile. You have five minutes before we go for the guards at the loading area,” Mercer said, pointing to his watch.

With a pained look, Joe quickly walked up Red River Street and turned around the corner to East Fourth, vanishing from their view.

Five minutes later, Mercer looked around and saw that David Donnelly was in position on the other side of the street, hiding behind a large live oak tree. He signaled with his hands that they were ready to proceed, and David acknowledged.

“Showtime,” Mercer said, feeling the syringe with the sedative they had found in the ambulance in his hand. He moved forward with Emily, who stepped up to the security station at the Austin Conference Center’s loading area at the back of the complex. Mercer hid behind a large concrete column two paces away, part of a fenced colonnade to secure the bay, watching carefully the angles of the surveillance cameras covering the gates.

“Excuse me, sir?” Emily smiled sweetly as she knocked on the open door’s Perspex window.

The young guard, who had been languidly tapping on his phone, jumped up and smiled awkwardly back, scratching his head. Emily figured that the kid in the high-visibility vest was probably a student worker.

“How can I help you, ma’am?”

“Look, my phone’s battery is empty, so I’ve no maps working. I’m already late for Jason Bolt’s keynote and can’t find the right entrance. Can you please help me?” Emily stepped back on the pavement to lure the kid out of the station and pointed in the direction opposite Mercer’s position. “Is this the correct way?”

Although she felt bad about what was about to happen, her smile didn’t show.

The guard didn’t see Mercer’s swift palm strike coming, dropping him instantly. His eyes rolled over, and Mercer caught the collapsing body, lowering him back into the security station. He took out the syringe with the sedative and injected it into his arm to make sure he would stay knocked out cold for the next hour.

Just as he was about to get the high-visibility vest of the guard, he heard a voice from the parking lot on the loading bay.

“Hey kid, you ok?” A man in a dark suit, smart glasses, and an FBI badge dangling from his neck walked over, his hand already on the way to the gun in the holster under his jacket.

The moment the agent had Mercer in the sights of his smart glasses, he would be busted, the facial recognition taking care of it. Mercer cursed. He should have expected that the FBI would watch Bolt’s transport, although nobody was in sight when he did his recon.

“Yeah, everything good,” he said half-heartedly, readying himself for a fight.

“What the fuck?!”

Mercer peered through the station’s window and saw the agent clutching his neck with a mixture of surprise and anger on his face, a dart sticking out from the side.

A moment later, he faltered, crumbling to the ground.

Mercer moved quickly. He grabbed the agent’s smart glasses and stomped on them. He dragged the man, who was much heavier than the security guard, into the station and laid him next to the student on the ground.

Looking to the other side of the street, he saw David giving him a thumbs-up to signal that the Dan-Inject was ready again. He realized there were four darts left.

Putting on the guard’s vest, he stepped out on the street. Emily had already left to get the ambulance from a nearby parking lot. After quickly looking around, he signaled David to come over.

Donnelly carried the gun over his shoulder and slipped into the security station.

“What is Hartman waiting for? Any minute, someone will check in on the agent, and the shit will hit the fan.” Mercer greeted him.

“All we can do now is take our positions and wait,” David said, taking the gun. “He’ll come through, I’m sure.”

A police siren wailed somewhere nearby

“He fucking better does,” Mercer swore as he left for the service elevator, and Emily drove the ambulance through the gate, “he fucking better does.”